Guide to the James Howard Whitty papers, 1792-1943 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Howard Whitty papers 1792-1943 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Whitty, J. H. (James Howard), 1859-1937
19 linear feet Extent: Approx. 12,275 Items
Journalist, businessman, Poe scholar and editor, and an avid collector of Poe memorabilia; resided in Richmond, Virginia. The James Howard Whitty papers include letters, drafts of books and articles, research notes, newspaper clippings, and other papers, all relating to Whitty's writings on Edgar Allan Poe's life and career, his editorship of Poe's poetry, and his relationship with other literary scholars. The numerous clippings are found both loose and mounted in three scrapbooks. There is also a manuscript volume containing a Richmond, Virginia book seller's accounts. Other research materials on Poe consist of transcripts of Poe's letters and over 600 images related to Poe's life. There is voluminous correspondence from Poe scholars and other literary critics, including George Woodberry, Mary E. Phillips, and Thomas O. Mabbott. Whitty's research papers also contain copies of letters from John C. Frémont to Joel Poinsett in 1838, research material and correspondence relating to Virginia planter and early Congressman John Randolph of Roanoke, and the history of Richmond, Virginia.
RL.01379
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Howard Whitty papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1941 and 1964.
Biographical Note
James Howard Whitty was a journalist, businessman, and scholar residing in Richmond, Virginia. Whitty was an avid collector of Poe memorabilia. In 1916 he became an organizer and later the first president of the Poe Foundation of the Poe Museum in Richmond, Virginia, leaving the foundation in 1924.
Collection Overview
Papers of James Howard Whitty, author and authority on the life and work of Edgar Allan Poe, are chiefly comprised of correspondence, research writings and notes, printed material such as clippings and engravings, and copies of 19th century correspondence, all relating to Whitty's writings on literary figures and Virginia history.
Whitty's research materials on Edgar Allen Poe include copies of a large number of letters by Edgar Allan Poe and members of his family; documents concerning the events surrounding Poe's death; a large amount of correspondence with other Poe scholars, particularly George E. Woodberry, Mary E. Phillips, and Thomas Ollive Mabbott; and research notes made by Whitty, including material for a complete Poe bibliography, and rough drafts of Whitty's writings on Poe. There are also over 600 images, chiefly engravings, including portraits of Poe and his family, images of the places where Poe lived, and the museums and shrines dedicated to him. In addition, there are letters relating to Whitty's work as organizer and first president of the Edgar Allan Poe shrine in Richmond, Virginia, and to Whitty's quarrel with the directors of the shrine in 1924.
The hundreds of clippings included in this collection consist of what seems to be almost every article or mention of Poe from 1900-1935. Many of the articles are in duplicate and many of them contain notations by Whitty. There are also three scrapbooks of clippings.
Other materials center on Whitty's interest in the history of Richmond, Virginia; business correspondence pertaining to Whitty's work on the staff of the Richmond Times; notes on and copies of correspondence of John Randolph of Roanoke, 1814-1816 (Virginia planter and Congressman) to Ann Morris, in which he accuses her of being a common prostitute and the murderess of her child and of his brother. Copies of her answers to his accusations are also included. Whitty was interested in writing on John Randolph of Roanoke, but apparently never did so. Additional research materials include notes on and copies of letters from John Charles Frémont to Joel R. Poinsett, 1838; and other printed material, including reviews, copies of sections of books, publication notices, and advertisements. There is also a manuscript volume containing the accounts of a Richmond bookseller, 1929-1936.
Subject Headings
Frémont, John Charles, 1813-1890; Mabbott, Thomas Ollive, 1898-1968; Phillips, Mary Elizabeth, 1857-1945; Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849; Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851; Randolph, John, 1773-1833; Whitty, J. H. (James Howard), 1859-1937; Woodberry, George Edward, 1855-1930; American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American; Authors -- Biography; Poets, American; Richmond (Va.) -- History; Virginia -- History; Scrapbooks
Related Material
David Kelly Jackson papers, 1850, 1925-1991 and undated (contain materials related to Poe history, and Whitty correspondence)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Joseph Francis Ambrose Jackson papers, 1829-1944 (contain letters from Whitty on Poe)
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- James Howard Whitty papers, 1792-1943 and undated, (38 boxes)
  - Facts about Edward Allan Poe (Box 1)
  - The first census of Richmond, Virginia (copy), 1792 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1839-1908 (Box 1)
    Contains letters from Poe and others as well as notes. Most of the correspondence in the collection relates to business matters regarding Poe's publications, as well as Poe's personal affairs.
  - Correspondence, 1909-1912 (Box 2)
    One letter from Evan Chesterman asks for help in resolving a conflict between Poe and the Richmond Examiner editor - Chesterman feels he is responsible for Poe challenging the editor to a duel.
  - Correspondence, 1916 June-December 1917 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1918 -1919 July (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1919 August-1921 July (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1921 August-1922 December (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1924 February (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1924 March-1925 June (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1925 July-March 1926 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1925 April-December 1925 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1928 April (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1921 August-1922 December (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1928 May-1930 May (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1930 June-December 1932 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1935 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1943 and undated (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes, undated (Box 17)
    Most of the undated papers and notes in this collection are by or about Poe and his publications.
  - Correspondence from Charles Campbell, Fredericksburg, Virginia, undated (Box 18)
    Campbell knew Whitty through Campbell's work on the Bland family, related to John Randolph of Roanoke.
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes, undated (Box 18)
  - The Randolph family papers (Box 19)
  - John Charles Frémont (Box 19)
    Includes notes, articles, and copies of letters.
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes, undated (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes, undated (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes, undated (Box 21)
  - Father Tall miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes, undated (Box 22)
  - Letters from Poe (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous papers and notes, undated (Box 23)
  - John R. Thompson's Edgar Allan Poe (Box 23)
  - Publications, 1621-1898 (Box 24)
    Publications in this collection primarily comprise magazines, literary and academic journals, leaflets, and books, by and about Poe.
  - Publications, 1902-1926 (Box 25)
  - Publications,1927-1937 and undated (Box 26)
  - Publications, undated (Box 27)
  - Publications, undated (Box 28)
  - Songs, lyrics from Poe's poems and others (Box 28)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 29-36)
    Include book reviews of Poe's own publications, articles regarding The Poe Museum and monuments, and Whitty's life and career.
  - Pictures (Box 37-38)
    Printed etchings and photos of The Poe Museum and memorial, other parts of Virginia (of general interest and related to Poe's history), people close to Poe (and unidentified individuals), illustrations (most of which were mostly likely used to accompany his writings in publications), portraits of Poe, postcards, and other images.
  - Manuscript account book, bookseller in Richmond, Virginia (24 pp.), 1929-1936 (Box 37-38, Volume F:2598)
  - Scrapbook (12 pp.), 1902-1930 (Box 37-38, Volume F:6474)
  - Scrapbook (18 pp.), 1909 (Box 37-38, Volume F:6475)
  - Scrapbook (79 pp.), 1908-1915 (Box 37-38, Volume F:6476)